Guide to the international history of photography collection, 1885-1951 RL.00616
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
International history of photography collection
1885-1951
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00616
3 Linear Feet 3 boxes 11 prints
Collection dates from 1885-1951 and comprises eleven vintage photographic prints by individuals considered to be master photographers. The prints are intended to represent major formats, techniques, and genres of the 19th and 20th centuries. Photographers whose prints are in the collection hail from Europe, the United States, and Mexico: Eugène Atget (printed by Berenice Abbot), Henri Cartier-Bresson, Alvin Langdon Coburn, Manuel Alvarez Bravo, F. Holland Day, Peter Henry Emerson, Lewis Hine, Aaron Siskind, Ralph Steiner, Alfred Stieglitz, and Minor White. Formats range from photogravures to gelatin silver prints, with the latter predominating; all are black-and-white and matted. Subjects include rural landscapes, individual and group portraits, and urban streetscapes. Acquired as part of the Archive for Documentary Arts at Duke University.
11 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. However, the prints cannot be photocopied or reproduced.
Researchers must wear gloves when handling the matted prints. Prints should always be picked up and supported with two hands. The prints cannot be removed from the mats, but researchers may open the window mat to see the full print. The Visual Materials Archivist must be consulted prior to any display of the photographs.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The prints in the International history of photography collection were purchased by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 2002-2008 and 2017.
Collection Overview
The International History of Photography collection dates from 1885-1951 and comprises eleven vintage photographic prints by individuals considered to be master photographers. The prints in this collection were acquired and assembled by the Rubenstein library staff, in part to provide students the opportunity to view and study original works from the world's foremost photographers as well as to learn about the major formats, techniques, and genres of the 19th and 20th centuries.
Photographers whose prints are in the collection hail from Europe, Mexico, and the United States: Eugène Atget (printed by American photographer Berenice Abbot), Henri Cartier-Bresson, Alvin Langdon Coburn, Manuel Alvarez Bravo, F. Holland Day, Peter Henry Emerson, Lewis Hine, Aaron Siskind, Ralph Steiner, Alfred Stieglitz, and Minor White. The print by Eugène Atget, Flower Man, was printed by well-known American photographer Berenice Abbot, who purchased part of Atget's negative archive in 1928.
Formats range from photogravures to gelatin silver prints, with the latter predominating; all are black-and-white and are matted. Subjects include rural landscapes, individual and group portraits, architecture, and urban streetscapes. The prints are sized from 4.5 x 6.5 inches to approximately 9.5 x 13.5 inches, and are all matted.
Researchers must wear gloves when handling the prints. Prints should always be picked up and supported with two hands. The prints cannot be removed from the mats, but researchers may open the window mat to see the full print. The Archive of Documentary Arts Curator must be consulted prior to any display of the photographs.
Acquired as part of the Archive for Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Documentary Photography -- History; Photographers -- United States; Photographers -- Europe; Photographers -- Mexico; Photography, Artistic -- History; Photography -- History; Gelatin silver prints; Black-and-white photographs; Photogravures; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Abbott, Berenice, 1898-1991; Day, F. Holland (Fred Holland), 1864-1933; Coburn, Alvin Langdon, 1882-1966; Bravo, Manuel Alvarez, 1902-2002; Atget, Eugène, 1857-1927; Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957 -- Portraits; Hine, Lewis Wickes, 1874-1940; Emerson, P. H. (Peter Henry), 1856-1936; White, Minor; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946; Steiner, Ralph, 1899-1986; Siskind, Aaron; Cartier-Bresson, Henri, 1908-2004
- International history of photography collection, 1886-1951, 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  All photographs are matted.
  - Henri Cartier-Bresson: Eighth century statue of the Buddha looking over a field of stupas towards Merapi Peak, Indonesia, 1949; Gelatin silver print, 9 1/4 x 13 1/2 inches (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Published in Life magazine, February 13, 1950.
    Title label is affixed to back of print with title in pencil; also present are a LIFE Picture Collection stamp, publication stamps, LIFE/Bresson credit stamp, date stamp, printer stamp, and notations.
  - Alvin Langdon Coburn: Wyndham Lewis, 1916 February 25; Photogravure, 6 1/8 x 8 1/2 inches; 11x14 inch mat (Box 1)
  - Lewis Hine: Young mill boys, Gastonia [N.C.], 1912 October 23; Gelatin silver print, 4.5 x 6.5 inches; 11x14 inch mat (Box 1)
  - Peter Henry Emerson: Towing the Reed, 1885; Platinum print, 16x20 inch mat (Box 2)
    Published in Life and Landscape on the Norfolk Broads in 1886.
  - Minor White: Sandblaster, 1949; Gelatin silver print, 8 1/2 x 9 7/8 inches; 16x20 inch mat (Box 2)
    Location is San Francisco. Signed by photographer on front; edition 71/100.
  - Ralph Steiner: No known title, circa 1915; Gelatin silver print; 11x14 inch mat (Box 2)
    Row of seven 19th century houses in urban setting, cars parked out front.
  - Aaron Siskind: North Carolina 30, 1951; Gelatin silver print; 11x14 inch mat (Box 2)
    Close-up of tattered outdoor advertisements on side of unidentified building. Printed later than 1951.
  - Alfred Stieglitz: Ploughing, 1904; Photogravure, 7 1/2 x 9 1/2 inches; 14x18 inch mat (Box 3)
    Image appeared in Stieglitz's journal Camera Work in October 1905, the first issue devoted to Stieglitz's own photographs since its inception in 1903.
  - Eugène Atget: Flower man, circa 1900-1910; Gelatin silver print, 6 1/2 x 9 1/2 inches; 14x18 inch mat (Box 3)
    Printed by Berenice Abbot around 1928.
    Stamped on verso: "photo E. Atget collection Berenice Abbot 1 W. 67th St."
  - Manuel Alvarez Bravo: Niño Maya de Tulum [Mayan Child of Tulum], Mexico, 1942; Gelatin silver print, 14x18 inch mat (Box 3)
  - F. Holland Day: No known title, circa 1905; Photogravure, 7 3/4 x 9 3/4 inches; 14x18 inch mat (Box 3)
    Bust-length portrait of Cora Folsom, a Hampton College teacher. Print is accompanied by photocopies of several letters from Folsom to Day regarding his visit to the campus, as well as photocopies of images of Folsom and pages from the Hampton yearbook. When acquired, print had small tear on right side.